Guide to the Peter A. Wick Collection of J. J. Grandville
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Peter A. Wick Collection of J. J. Grandville
1827-1846
GEN MSS 1301
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.4
3 boxes
A collection of sketches and prints by French artist J. J. Grandville.
Wick, Peter A.
Grandville, J. J., 1803-1847
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Peter A. Wick (Yale 1943) and Kathleen Wick, 1995-2003.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Drawings, 1829-1846. II. Prints, 1827-1835.
Peter Arms Wick (1920-2004)
Peter Arms Wick (1920-2004, Yale 1943), American author and bibliophile, held curatorial positions in the Prints and Drawings Department of the Museum of Fine Arts Boston, and at Harvard University's Fogg Art Museum and Houghton Library.
J. J. Grandville (1803-1847)
J. J. Grandville (1803-1847), French caricaturist, born Jean Ignace Isidore Gérard, who. He specialized in political and social satire presented in popular journals, books, and collections of fables illustrated with anthropomorphic animals and insects
Associated Materials
J. J. Grandville, Grande course au clocher académique (GEN MSS 1325), Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of twenty-eight drawings and forty lithographs by the French artist and caricaturist J. J. Grandville. The drawings are ink, graphite, and watercolor on paper, and are sketches that he created prior to the final drawings for illustrations for the books Fables de Florian, Jérôme Paturot, Les Métamorphoses du jour, Petites misères de la vie humaine, Scènes de la vie privée et publique des animaux, and Voyages de Gulliver dans des contrées lointaines. The lithographs are images published in the journals La Caricature and Le Charivari, with a separate porfolio of ten prints titled Chaque âge a ses plaisirs.
Caricature -- Illustrations; Charivari -- Illustrations; Métamorphoses du jour -- Illustrations; Petites misères de la vie humaine -- Illustrations; Scènes de la vie privée et publique des animaux -- Illustrations; Animals -- Caricatures and cartoons; Animals in art; Artists -- France; Caricatures and cartoons -- France; French wit and humor; Human-animal relationships -- Caricatures and cartoons; Human behavior -- Caricatures and cartoons; Illustrators -- France; Caricatures -- France -- 19th century; Drawings (visual works) -- France -- 19th century; Lithographs -- France -- 19th century; Satires (Visual works) -- France -- 19th century; Artists -- France -- 19th century; Illustrators -- France -- 19th century; Florian, 1755-1794 ( Fables de Florian, Illustrations); Grandville, J. J., 1803-1847; Reybaud, Louis, 1799-1879 ( Jérôme Paturot, Illustrations); Swift, Jonathan, 1667-1745 ( Gulliver's travels, French, Illustrations); Wick, Peter A.
- Drawings, 1829-1846; Series I; 0.21; 1 box
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged by title of publication, with unidentified drawings filed at the end.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains twenty-eight drawings and sketches for book illustrations.
  - Fables de Florian (Paris: J.-J. Dubochet, 1842)
    - "Le lièvre, ses amis et les deux chevreuils" (fable VII); ink and graphite on paper, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jérôme Paturot à la recherche d'une position sociale (Paris: Dubochet le Chevalier, 1846
    - "Malvina," page 16; ink and graphite on paper, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Le grand-Mapa," page 20; ink and graphite on paper, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - L'illustration: journal universel (Paris: J.J. Dubochet, 1843-)
    - "Le Marchand de Hannetons," in no. 3, May 4, 1844; ink on paper (Box 1, Folder 4)
      With wood engraving cut from journal.
  - Les Métamorphoses du jour (Paris: Garnier frères, 1829)
    - "Un misanthrope," opposite p. 75; ink and watercolor on paper, 1829 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "Il y a plenitude, nouse vous saignerons demain," opposite p. 435; ink on card, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Mounted on verso of printed ticket to the Goldsmith's Ball, London, February 13, 1851
  - Petites misères de la vie humaine (Paris: H. Fournier, 1843)
    - Study for frontispiece; graphite and ink on paper, 1843 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Accompanied by undated printed version.
  - Scènes de la vie privée et publique des animaux (Paris: J. Hetzel et Paulin, 1842)
    Preliminary drawings for illustrations
    - Frontispiece, vol. 1; ink on paper, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Prologue, vol. 1, p. 2; ink on paper, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Pour payer le propriétaire," vol. 1, opposite p. 65, and "Il y a des hommes," opposite p. 75; ink on paper, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Quand on ne tient pas á voir lever l'aurore," vol. 1, opposite p. 72; ink on paper, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Cour criminelle de justice animale," vol. 1, opposite p. 156; ink on paper, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Cul de lampe," vol. 1, page 260; ink on paper, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Sketch drawn on page proof from Voyage d'un moineau de paris.
    - "Voyage d'un lion d'Afrique a Paris," vol. 1, opposite p. 365; ink on paper, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Five small sketches, vol. 1; ink on paper, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Peregrination memorable du doyen des crapauds," vol. 2, opposite p. 92; ink on paper, 1842 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Voyages de Gulliver dans des contrées lointaines (Paris: Imprimerie de H. Fournier, 1838)
    - Two drawings, vol. 1, chapter 1, p. 27 and 38, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      With blind stamp of the Grandville estate sale.
  - Unidentified
    - "Concert d'Insectes"; graphite, brown ink and brown and gray wash on paper, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Possibly for Le Magasin pittoresque.
    - "Little Courtesies"; ink on paper, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - [Council of ministers]; ink on paper, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "L'amiable Prince de [ ]; ink on paper, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - [Two cats]; ink and watercolor on buff paper, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
      Pair of drawings: a male and female cat, anthromorphized
- Prints, 1827-1835; Series II; 1.4; 2 boxes
  The series contains forty-one lithographs, primarily from the journal La Caricature.
  Series II is arranged alphabetically by title of publication.
  - La Caricature (Paris: Aubert, 1831-35)
    - "La Grippe," from no. 36, pl.72, 1831 July 7 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "Ce n'est pas une Chambre, c'est un chenil," from no. 44, pl. 89, 1831 September 1 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - "Une Fourneé de galettes" from no. 54, pl. 109, 1831 November 11 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - "Singeries morales, politiques, etc.," from no. 77, pl. 154-155, 1832 April 19 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - "Singeries morales, politiques, etc.," from no. 79, pl. 158-159, 1832 May 3 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - "Pauvre France!," from no. 82, pl. 164, 1832 May 24 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - "Le Pouvoir use les hommes," from no. 92, pl. 187, 1832 August 9 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      Two copies
    - "Rien n'est si dangereux qu'un ignorant," from No. 93, pl. 191, 1832 August 16 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - "Pendant qu'il plume son coq," from no. 100, pl. 203, 1832 October 4 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - "Ils ne savent plus á quel saint se vouer," from no. 102, pl. 210, 1832 October 18 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - "La Chair est faible," from no. 107, pl. 221-222, 1832 November 22 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - "Poulaupair gargotier," from no. 111, pl. 229, 1832 December 20 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - "Écritoire monarchique," from no. 142, pl. 298, 1833 July 25 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - "Trés humbles et très dèvouês gardes nationaux" from no. 159, pl. 332, 1833 November 21 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - "Un joli bouquet" from no. 163, pl. 343, 1833 December 20 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - "Enigme," from no. 166, pl. 350, 1834 January 9 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - "La Main invisible," from no. 170, pl. 361, 1834 February 13 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - "Imitation libre d'un tableau de M. Horace Vernet," from no. 179, pl. 376-377, 1834 April 30 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - "Hé bien! vous devez être content?," from no. 191, pl. 401, 1834 July 3 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - "Théatre royal des marionettes," from no. 204, pl. 426, 1834 October 2 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - "Grande course aux portefeuilles," from no. 230, pl. 479, 1835 April 2 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - "O soliel de juillet, viens vite," from no. 231, pl. 481, 1835 April 9 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - "Judgement des Juges," from no. 233, pl. 484-485, 1835 April 23 (Box 3, Folder 48)
      Two copies, one cropped to the image
  - Chaque âge a ses plaisirs (Paris: Chez Gihaut, 1827) (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Series of ten lithographs titled "Les amusemens de l'enfance" (3 pl.),"Les plaisirs de la jeunesse" (3 pl.), "Les jouissances de l'âge mûr" (3 pl.), and "Les passe-temps de la vieillesse."
  - Le Charivari (Paris: Imprimerie d'Auffray, 1832-)
    - L'Auberge des Adrets: "Eh bien camarades! Comment supportez vous l'existence?", 1834 February 18 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Les Parisiens pittoresques: "Une Saisie", 1835 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      Plate 2 from a suite of six lithographs published in between September 30 and November 29, 1835